<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-17T22:28:38+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">dr-marco’s blog</title><subtitle>dr-marco&apos;s blog</subtitle><author><name>dr-marco</name></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Not every published model is a valid benchmark</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/15/plastic-waste-detection" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not every published model is a valid benchmark" /><published>2025-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/10/15/plastic-waste-detection-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/15/plastic-waste-detection"><![CDATA[<p>Training a model with deep learning techniques can be a total pain if you don’t 
know how to set up your hyperparameters properly. To avoid the headache, you can
tune them and find the subset of values that will optimize the performance of 
your model. Or, if you’re short on time, you can do a little research and see if 
somebody already did the tuning part. You can snag their hyperparameters 
configuration and also take their results as a benchmark for your model. The 
whole point of doing that is to get a starting point for your tuning and a 
benchmark to improve, if possible. This is pretty much what I wanted to do in 
one of the last projects that I did at university.</p>

<h3 id="my-assignment">My assignment</h3>

<p>My assignment was to train a model that is able to detect plastic waste on water 
surfaces like rivers and lakes. I worked with a friend of mine, and we both 
decided to use the YOLOv8 architecture and train it with a dataset that was 
available for our project.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> 
We did some experiments without any great results 
in performance, so we looked around for academic papers or some posts on the 
internet that seemed relevant. 
We mostly bumped into papers about detection with 
datasets containing satellite images… except for one study published in early 
2024<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> that was related to our exact same dataset and model. Lucky us. 
So, 
after reading the paper, we found out that we could reach good performance with 
a specific configuration. Nice!</p>

<p>Let’s try if we can replicate those results and… nope, still got garbage 
results with high evaluation loss. Maybe we ran the training with some different 
hyperparameter or other details. Let’s try again, but with the exact same values 
as hyperparameters. Still nothing. The performance just wouldn’t budge.</p>

<h3 id="wtf">WTF?!</h3>

<p>It seems reasonable to look for bugs or misconfigurations on our end (after all, 
I was only a master’s student), but when <em>nothing</em> you try is able to give better 
results, you start to have some doubts.</p>

<p>Are we sure that the performance shown in the paper is legit? Is there some kind 
of catch in it?</p>

<p>So, to answer that, we had to do only one thing: find a method to replicate 
their results, even if it meant making stupid assumptions about the dataset, 
model, or techniques. And we did it. We kept making “wrong” configurations until 
we found out that the problem with the academic study wasn’t in the 
hyperparameters at all, but with how they used the dataset.</p>

<p>Trivia: what happens if you train a model with a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">train</code> set (as in, a dataset 
used for the training phase) and then you use the very same <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">train</code> set also as 
the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> set (as in, the dataset whose whole purpose is to validate the model)? 
Spoiler: you get amazing-looking results but the <em>same shitty model</em>.</p>

<h3 id="diving-into-details">Diving into details</h3>

<p>The dataset used <sup id="fnref:1:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> contains 3 different subsets, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">train</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">test</code>, 
each designed for its specific purpose, as I mentioned in that sarcastic 
question earlier (the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">test</code> set is used to test the model once the training 
phase is completed).
Inside each subset, there are a bunch of different images labeled with 4 
different kinds of classes using the YOLO specification (see the <a href="https://docs.ultralytics.com/datasets/detect/">YOLO documentation</a> to learn more about it).</p>

<p>In order to evaluate how good the model is, many metrics are used like precision, 
recall and loss functions. 
In particular for object detection models, the main loss functions are the 
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">box_loss</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cls_loss</code>. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cls_loss</code> (classification loss) tells us the 
misclassification rate, and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">box_loss</code> (box loss) tells us the error during 
the drawing of the box over the detected objects.
But one of the best metrics that summarizes how good the detection model really 
is is the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mAP50</code>: mean average precision over all classes used.
Again, for more details about the metrics that can be used in object detection 
models check the documentation <a href="https://docs.ultralytics.com/guides/yolo-performance-metrics/">here</a>.</p>

<p>For simplicity, I’ll just talk about the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mAP50</code> here: this percentage metric 
just means “higher is better”, with 100% being perfect.</p>

<p>With our actual tests (using the correct <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> set, )we were only able to reach 
an overall <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mAP50</code> of 39.1%. This wasn’t very good, since the model was good 
with a specific class, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PLASTIC_BOTTLE</code> and bad with the others. And as you can 
see in the following graphs there is no margin of improvement because the model 
would just overfit with extra training.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/plastic_detection/results_1.png" alt="Loss functions and metrics of our trained model" />
<em>Loss functions and metrics of our (legit) trained model</em></p>

<p>As you can see, these metrics weren’t nearly as good as those in the paper. The 
authors claimed their model could reach 68.8%!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/plastic_detection/results_2.png" alt="Loss functions and metrics of the paper model" /> 
<em>Loss functions and metrics from the paper (sorry for bad image resolution)</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/plastic_detection/results_3.png" alt="Loss functions and metrics matching paper model" width="1440px" />
<em>And look at that! Our results when we copy their mistake. Quite the same behavior</em></p>

<h3 id="ok-why-is-it-bad">Ok, why is it bad?</h3>

<p>So, why is this so bad?
As you can see from our “fake” results (that third image), the metrics look 
amazing. The validation loss plummets, and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mAP50</code> shoots up to 62.1%, pretty 
much just like the paper claimed.
But the model isn’t learning anything. It’s memorizing.</p>

<p>Think of it this way: It’s like giving a student a 100-question practice test 
and then making their final exam the exact same 100 questions. The student would 
get a perfect score, right? But did they actually learn the subject? Hell no. 
They just memorized the answers.</p>

<p>That’s exactly what’s happening here. The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> set is supposed to be the “real 
test” to check if the model can generalize—if it can find plastic in new images 
it’s never seen before.
By using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">train</code> set as the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> set, the model just memorizes the training 
data. It’s not learning to detect the features of a plastic bottle; it’s 
learning “in image_123.jpg, there is a box at [x, y, w, h].” This is the classic 
definition of overfitting, and it’s a massive ML mistake.</p>

<p>The model looks like a genius on paper, but it’s completely useless in the real 
world. The second you’d give it an actual new photo from the test set, it would 
fail hard.</p>

<p>So the big takeaway? Always be skeptical. Just because something is “published” 
doesn’t mean it’s correct. Always try to replicate the results, and if something 
looks fishy (or way too good to be true), it probably is. Trust your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">val</code> set… 
as long as it’s the right one!</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Dataset used: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plastic_in_river</code>. Unfortunately the dataset is not available anymore. <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20240821170803/https://huggingface.co/datasets/kili-technology/plastic_in_river">Here</a> the wayback machine archive linking dataset page from huggingface in August 2024. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>Plastic Waste on Water Surfaces Detection Using Convolutional Neural Networks</em>: <a href="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3668/paper13.pdf">Here</a> you can read the paper <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>dr-marco</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Training a model with deep learning techniques can be a total pain if you don’t know how to set up your hyperparameters properly. To avoid the headache, you can tune them and find the subset of values that will optimize the performance of your model. Or, if you’re short on time, you can do a little research and see if somebody already did the tuning part. You can snag their hyperparameters configuration and also take their results as a benchmark for your model. The whole point of doing that is to get a starting point for your tuning and a benchmark to improve, if possible. This is pretty much what I wanted to do in one of the last projects that I did at university.]]></summary></entry></feed>